A Guide to the Virginia Constitutional Convention (1850-1851) 1850-1851
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records, 1850-1851
Library of Virginia
35189-35195
1.43 cubic feet
Virginia Constitutional Convention (1850-1851)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred prior to 1905.
Historical Information
Dissatisfaction on the part of the counties in western Virginia over the provisions of the constitution of 1830 relating to representation in the General Assembly led to repeated calls for a new constitutional convention. After several years without success, those in favor of a new constitution saw a bill to the question before the public pass the General Assembly on March 4, 1850. It was ordered that 10,000 copies of the bill be printed and distributed throughout the state. The voters approved the referendum overwhelmingly and on October 14, 1850 the convention assembled in Richmond. The delegates met for slightly more than nine months and considered many documents pertaining to statistical studies of land valuation, taxation rates, literacy, debts and liabilities of Virginia, and internal improvements in the hopes of producing constitutional reform that would end the sectional strife in Virginia. The convention made many changes to the constitution adopted by the convention of 1829-1830, but the most important change made was that concerning the qualification of voters, which was changed to allow every white male citizen of the Commonwealth, twenty-one years of age, who had been a resident for two years, to be qualified to vote. The people also got the right to elect the Governor, who prior to that time was elected by the General Assembly. The convention adjourned on August 1, 1851, and on the 23, 24 and 25 of October the constitution that it drafted was submitted to the voters, who approved it by a vote of 75,748 to 11,060.
Scope and Content Information
The Virginia Constitutional Convention records are organized into two series. Series have been designated for Election records and Convention records.
Series #1: Election Records, 1850-1851. This series is divided into three sub-series: Subseries A: Convention Election Returns, 1850 April 25. This subseries is composed of abstracts of votes from the special election held 1850 April 25 on the question of holding a convention to amend the state constitution. The abstracts are attachments to letters to the governor from the county clerks and election officials detailing the number of votes for and against the convention. Charles City County submitted a poll book listing the name of the voter and how they voted.
Subseries B: Election Returns for Delegates, 1850 August 26 - September 3. This subseries consists of election certificates from the special election held to elect delegates to the state constitutional convention of 1850-1851. The election was held 1850 August 22. The certificates list the names of delegates elected from Virginia's 37 election districts. Subseries C: Referendum Election Returns, 1851 October 23- 25. This subseries consists of abstracts of votes and/or poll books from the referendum for ratifying or rejecting the amended state constitution. The referendum was held 1851 October 23-25. The results arrived in letters from county clerks and sheriffs enumerating votes for and against the constitution and include a final tally of votes listed by county.
Series #2: Convention Records, 1850-1851 This series includes a minute book of the convention proceedings (1850 April 4 - 1851 August 1) and attendance books that list each delegate, noting their days of attendance at the convention. These volumes also serve as account books, noting payment for attendance and reimbursement for travel expenses. General Records include petitions and memorials to the convention arranged chronologically, letters concerning statistical information and miscellaneous letters, miscellaneous committee reports, and records concerning convention expenses. Also included is a list of elected delegates arranged numerically by voting district with a description of each of the districts.
Organization
Organized into the following two (2) series: I. Election Records, 1850-1851; and II. Convention Records, 1850-1851.
Contents List
- Series I: Election Records, 1850-1851
  arranged chronologically by date of election; alphabetical by locality there in
  - Subseries A: Convention Election Returns, 1850 April 25 (accession 35189)
    - Accomack County - Lee County (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lewis County - York County; Cities of Norfolk, Petersburg, Richmond and Williamsburg (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries B: Election Returns for Delegates, 1850 August 26 - September 3 (accession 35190)
    - District 1 - District 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - District 20 - District 37 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries C: Referendum Election Returns, 1851 October 25 - November 12 (accession 35191)
    - Accomack County - Cumberland County (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dinwiddie County - Lunenburg County (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Madison County - Putnam County (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Raleigh County - York County (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Norfolk City, Petersburg, Richmond City and Williamsburg (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Convention Records, 1850-1851
  - Minute Book, 1850 April 4 - 1851 August 1 (accession 35193) (Box 2, Folder Volume)
  - Attendance Books, 1850-1851 (accession 35194) (Box 2, Folder two volumes)
  - Petitions and Memorials, 1850-1851 (accession 35195) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Petitions and Memorials, no date (see also oversize) (accession 35195) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters concerning statistical information, 1850-1851 (accession 35195) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1850-1851 (accession 35195) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Committee Reports, 1851 (accession 35195) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Papers concerning printing of convention proceedings, 1850-1851 (accession 35195) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Resolutions and papers concerning expenses (accession 35195) (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Oversized - Series I: Election Records
  - Subseries C: Referendum Election Returns, Statement of Vote on Proposed Constitutional Amendment, 1851 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Oversize - Series II: Convention Records
  - Petitions and Memorials, no date (accession 35195) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - List of Delegates, 1850 (accession 35192) (Box 4, Folder 3)